Alexander Thorne





+420 737 208 621



alex.thorne@gmail.com



www.alexthorne.site



linkedin.com/in/alexanderthorne

About Me

For the last ten years I've committed myself to the Energy M7 Product Line of Deutsche Börse and our continued aim to deliver best-in-class commodities trading platforms via true agile software development methodologies and everything-as-code driven infrastructure and delivery systems. I'm a process specialist with a continued record of establishing efficient, sustainable process areas and highly performant teams. I'm an experienced leader adept at cultivating effective team dynamics and healthy organizations. I'm a seasoned communications expert with experience in developing and conveying strategy. I'm committed to service excellence and delivering phenomenal customer care. And I'm a dedicated team member with a strong sense of ownership willingess to do whatever it takes to help my teams meet their goals.

Experience

Head of unit: M7 Gas & Observability Deutsche Börse

Jun 2024 - Present

Engineering manager responsible for two newly created software development and devops teams responsible for building two new products: a next-generation energy commodities trading platform, and an in-house PaaS offering for scalable Prometheus, OpenTelemetry, and OpenSearch based observability services.

- Formed a new platform engineering team to provide new products' infrastructure platform leveraging Google Cloud Platform's Kubernetes Engine (GKE)
- Championed R&D and business development of the M7 Observability Product
- Led cloud migration project from AWS and on-prem hosting to GCP
- Launched our division's first Products to reach fully compliant status (KRITIS) running material workloads on Google Cloud Platform 2015 - 2024
- Led the transition to a GitOps approach for Continuous Delivery of infrastructure and software

Head of Unit: Energy Operations Deutsche Börse

Apr 2020 - Jun 2024

Head of IT Operations for the M7 product line, Europe's premier power-spot trading platforms delivering highly performant, highly reliable services 24/7. Responsible for defining our operational strategies and service design. Engineering manager responsible leading multiple teams of highly skilled DevOps engineers and service management specialists committed to ensuring our Products' continued service excellence.

- Led continued migration to an in-house Operations department and shift from a waterfall-driven to a product-based Agile organization, utilizing LeSS, Scrum, and SRE/DevOps principles to create a series of products managed by cross-functional, highly autonomous delivery teams.
- Achieved an improved service availability from under 99.8% to a consistent 99.99%+ annual up-time for our flagship products.
- Asset owner for our product lines infrastructure fleet and all third-party vendor services
- Led various large scale infrastructure migration projects
- Managed large-scale infrastructure migration projects, ensuring seamless transitions for our product line.

Head of Unit: Energy Business Operations Jan 2018 – Apr 2020 Deutsche Börse

Head of the newly formed Energy Business Operations team, leading the migration to an in-house agile product-focused IT operations department from previous in-sourced and outsourced services.

- Developed a scalable, lean service management process by harmonizing service agreements, consolidating input streams and introducing the role of "Business Operations" to manage service delivery.
- Championed the migration from various issue management and customer-relationship management systems to a consolidated Jira Service Desk and Jira Software platform.
- Refactored customer agreements and Release Management processes to achieve continuous delivery of our software to production.

Skills

Leadership

- Communication
- Process Optimization
- Strategic Planning & Business
 Development
- Client Relations
- Vendor Management

DevOps & Site Reliability Engineering

- CI/CD & Automation: Jenkins, GitHub Actions
- Infrastructure as Code (IaC): Terraform,
 Ansible
- Observability & Monitoring:
 Prometheus, OpenTelemetry,
 OpenSearch, Grafana
- GitOps & Deployment: ArgoCD
- Failover & High Availability: Zerodowntime deployments, seamless failover strategies

Infrastructure & Cloud Computing

- Cloud Platforms: AWS, Google Cloud
- Virtualization: VMware
- Containerization & Orchestration:
 Docker, Kubernetes

IT Systems Administration & Security

- IT Systems & Service Architecture
- System Integration & Release
 Management
- Disaster Recovery & Business
 Continuity Planning
- IT Service Management (ITSM): ITIL
 Framework, COBIT, Service Design
- Jira Software, Jira Service Desk & Confluence: Technical Administration and Service Design

Project & IT Service Management

- Agile Methodologies: Scrum, Kanban, LeSS
- Risk Management & Compliance
- Technical Project Management
- Business & Functional Analysis

Programming & Scripting

Languages: Python, Bash, Java (for test automation)

Experience

DevOps Engineer, Service Implementation
Oct 2016 – Jan 2018
Deutsche Börse - Prague, Czechia

Member of the Service Implementation team, supporting transition of software development projects to release to customer.

- Planned and coordinated systems integration requirements for customer acceptance testing and production release of large scale software development projects for Deutsche Boerse's M7 Energy products
- Supported migration to an IaC delivery approach using Ansible & Jenkins for our full product line, ensuring seamless failover and zero-downtime production deployments.
- Led business and functional analysis to determine non-functional product requirements including backup, recovery, and data archiving; seamless failover and zero-downtime production deployments.
- Responsible for disaster recovery planning and testing

Software Development Engineer in Test Deutsche Börse - Prague, Czechia

Mar 2015 – present

Responsible for test automation, development and maintenance of test tools, test planning, test management and coordination, non-functional systems testing, networking and systems administration, integration and deployment processes.

- Developed and maintained test automation suite using Selenium WebDriver for Java.
- Created test tools for our development teams, including test environment virtualization and its deployment automation.
- Responsible for test planning and coordination of both feature and nonfunctional, technical systems testing for multiple large scale release projects.
- Supported development & maintenance of continuous integration and delivery processes for software development projects.

Hardware & Software Technician Apple, Inc. - Sunnyvale, California

Oct 2011 – Apr 2014

Senior technician responsible service and support for Apple hardware devices and OSX & iOS softwares. Service management process specialist responsible for developing and streamlining service strategies. Hardware repair technician certified for all Apple hardware products. Mentored and assisted team members in advanced troubleshooting and diagnostics.

Education & Language

Bachelor of Fine Arts: Spatial Arts
San Jose State University

2005 - 2009

German (C1, TestDaf certified)

Czech (B1)

References

Jens Rick

CIO, EEX

Antoine Vigues

Director - Energy IT, Deutsche Boerse

contact: on request contact: on request